Guide to the Democratic Party, Allegheny County, Pa., Seventh Ward Committee, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1970-1987 AIS.1987.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Democratic Party, Allegheny County, Pa., Seventh Ward Committee, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1970-1987
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Democratic Party (Allegheny County, Pa.). Seventh Ward Committee (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1987.07
0.63 Linear Feet (355 items)
The material in this collection reflects the activities of the Seventh Ward Committee (Pittsburgh) of the Democratic Party of Allegheny County, Pa. from 1970 to the present. It includes minutes, agendas, calls to meetings, correspondence, informational guides, voters' guides, Democratic Party primary elections, election campaign files, and news clippings.
History
In the 1970s, the Seventh Ward Committee (Pittsburgh) of the Democratic Party (Allegheny County, Pa.) evolved into a liberal and reform minded group. The committee sought to introduce initiatives within a formal party structure.
Scope and Content Notes
The material in this collection reflects the activities of the Seventh Ward Committee (Pittsburgh) of the Democratic Party of Allegheny County, Pa. from 1970 to 1987. It includes minutes, agendas, calls to meetings, correspondence, informational guides, voters' guides, Democratic Party primary elections, election campaign files, and news clippings. The largest single group of material within this collection is the monthly meeting minutes of the committee, which covers the years 1970-1984, with some gaps. The minutes are a good record of the committee's activities and accomplishments. Another group of particular interest is the Voters' Guide prepared by the committee for ward voters; the guides contain a profile of all Democratic candidates in a given primary election from 1976 to 1987. Most of the remaining material, consisting of correspondence, committee files, and publicity, covers the years 1970-1972 and centers around Ward Chairman James V. Cunningham. These records reflect the liberal, reform orientation of the committee during this period. Subjects of reform for the committee included city government and party organization and rules.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Richard L. Miller, member of the Seventh Ward Committee, 1987
Previous Citation
Democratic Party, Allegheny County, Pa., Seventh Ward Committee, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1970-, AIS.1987.07, Archives Services Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Allegheny County (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Government; Politics; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Elections -- Pennsylvania; Political parties -- Pennsylvania; Democratic Party (Allegheny County, Pa.). Seventh Ward Committee (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Meetings, 1970-1984; I.; 167 items
  - Meeting minutes, 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meeting agendas, early 1970s, 1976, 1977, 1979, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Call to meetings, early 1970s, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1970-1972, 1980-1982; II.; 36 items
  - Outgoing (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Contains letters to party officials, government officials and representatives concerning primaries/elections and current political issues, i.e., Home Rule Charter, busing, Nabisco plant closing, etc.
  - Incoming (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letters received from party and government officials concerning party issues, meetings and endorsements.
- Committee Files, 1970-1972, 1978; III.; 22 items
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains copies of statements made by Seventh Ward Committee Chairman, James V. Cunningham, at a public hearing of the rules committee of the Allegheny County Democratic Committee and at city council on the proposed 1971 city budget, memoranda, press releases, and reports by subcommittees, i.e., subcommittee on government services, on candidates, etc.
  - Committee membership lists, 1970-1972 and undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Activities, 1970-1987; IV.; 61 items
  - Information Guides, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Contains names, addresses and telephone numbers of state and city elected officials, party officials, civic and political organizations, fire, police, hospital, etc.
  - Voters' Guides, 1974, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Contains the names of all Democratic candidates who appeared on the ballot in the primary election of a given year. Each name appears with a short evaluation of the candidate's experience together with policy positions and political endorsements. Also contains names of Seventh Ward committee members and locations of polling places.
  - Events, 1970-1975, 1977-1978, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Contains announcements, posters and flyers of events such as candidate night, registration drive, movie party, fund raising, etc.
- Election Campaigns, 1970-1972, 1976, 1979, 1981-1982; V.; 51 items
  Scope and Content Notes
  File includes a variety of memorabilia, i.e., "Get out and vote leters," support letters to election day volunteers, candidate memorabilia, election tabulation, sample ballots.
  - November election, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Primary election, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - November election, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Primary election, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - November election, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - November election, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Primary election, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Primary election, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Primary election, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Publicity, 1970-1972; VI.; 18 items
  - Newspaper articles, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Re: local Democratic Party activities; most of the articles either quote or mention James V. Cunningham.
  - Newspaper articles, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Re: James V. Cunningham's bid for Seventh Ward Committee Chairman.
  - Newspaper articles, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Re: James V. Cunningham's bid for city council.